Guide to the Alfred de Liagre Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Alfred de Liagre papers
1927-1987
MS 1474
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
4.75
(6 boxes)
The papers contain correspondence, manuscripts and typescripts, photographs, and printed material relating to the careeer of Alfred de Liagre as theatrical producer and director.
De Liagre, Alfred, 1904-1987
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Mrs. Alfred de Liagre, 1987; Christina de Liagre, 2010.
Biographical / Historical
Alfred Gustav Etienne de Liagre was born on October 6, 1904 in Passaic, New Jersey, the son of Alfred and Frida (Unger) de Liagre. He was a graduate of the Riverdale Country School in New York City (1922), and Yale University (1926).
After brief careers in aviation, banking, and journalism, de Liagre entered the theatrical profession in 1930 as a stage hand at the Woodstock Playhouse, and as a stage manager for a production of Twelfth Night at Maxine Elliott's Theatre in New York. With his 1933 production of Three Cornered Moon, de Liagre began a career as a Broadway producer and director which spanned fifty-four years and included over forty stage and screen productions.
Among de Liagre's most successful productions were The Voice of the Turtle by John Van Druten, which de Liagre directed and co-produced with Richard Aldrich; Giradoux's Madwoman of Chaillot, which received the New York Drama Critics Circle Award in 1949; The Golden Apple, which received the "Best Musical" award of the New York Drama Critics in 1954; the 1958 production of Archibald MacLeish's J.B., which received the Tony Award; Deathtrap, which was produced in 1978, and was the longest running comedy thriller in Broadway history; and the revival of the Rogers and Hart musical On Your Toes which received the Tony Award in 1983.
De Liagre's film credits include Springtime for Henry, which he directed in 1934, The Voice of the Turtle, which he produced in 1947, and Deathtrap which he produced in 1981.
In addition to his Broadway productions, de Liagre produced a number of revivals in the late 1960s and 1970s for the Plumstead Playhouse, which he assisted in founding, and the American National Theatre and Academy, for which he served as executive director.
De Liagre was on the board of directors of the League of New York Theatres, the Actors Fund of America, the National Repertory Theatre, the American Theatre Wing, and the Julliard School, and was chairman of the School of Drama division of the Yale University Council. He was a member of the Century Club and of the Century's Round Table.
For his 1949 production of Madwoman of Chaillot, de Liagre was made a Chevalier in the French Legion of Honor. He was elected to the Theater Hall of Fame in 1984.
De Liagre was married to actress Mary Howard in 1945, and was the father of Christina and Nicholas de Liagre. Alfred de Liagre died on March 5, 1987.
Scope and Contents
The Alfred de Liagre Papers contain correspondence, manuscripts and typescripts, printed material, and photographs relating to de Liagre's career as a Broadway theater producer and director. The papers are arranged in three series and one addition: I. Correspondence, II. Subject Files, III. Photographs.
The bulk of Series I, CORRESPONDENCE, includes de Liagre's correspondence with playwrights, actors, and directors relating to his own productions and those of others. De Liagre's correspondence with John Van Druten regarding The Voice of the Turtle(folders 2-10 and 40-42) forms the largest group of letters relating to a single production. Other correspondents include Elmer Rice (folders 8 and 9), Clive Brook (folders 13-16), Beth Wendel and Aldous Huxley (folders 16-19), and Archibald MacLeish (folders 19-21). Included in the correspondence dating from 1970 to 1987 are letters that document de Liagre's involvement with the American National Theatre and Academy, the Century Club, and other professional and social organizations.
Series II, SUBJECT FILES, consists of manuscripts and typescripts of speeches and reminiscences, printed material, clippings, and legal and financial documents relating to de Liagre's personal and professional interests. The bulk of the material consists of clippings and programs relating to de Liagre's stage productions.
Series III, PHOTOGRAPHS, and the addition, consist of photoprints of de Liagre, individual actors and actresses, and theatrical productions.
Arrangement
The papers are arranged in three series and one addition: I. Correspondence, II. Subject Files, III. Photographs.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Theatrical producers and directors -- New York (State) -- New York; Photoprints; Brook, Clive, 1887-1974; De Liagre, Alfred, 1904-1987; Huxley, Aldous, 1894-1963; MacLeish, Archibald, 1892-1982; Rice, Elmer, 1892-1967; Van Druten, John, 1901-1957; Wendel, Beth; ANTA (Organization); Century Association (New York, N.Y.)
- CORRESPONDENCE, 1937-1986; Series I; 1' (2 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains material arranged chronologically. Undated material is arranged alphabetically by sender at the end of the series.
  - 1937, 1939, 1943-1949, 1950 June-Dec, undated, 1951-1959, 1961-1962, 1966, 1968, 1970-1974 (Box 1, Folder 1-22)
  - 1975-1984 Oct, 1985 January-1986 June (Box 2, Folder 23-38)
  - Undated
    - B-S (Box 2, Folder 39)
    - Van Druten, John (Box 2, Folder 40-41)
    - Van Druten, John - Weiss, Mark B. (Box 2, Folder 42)
    - Unidentified (Box 2, Folder 43)
- SUBJECT FILES, 1930-1987; Series II; 0.5; (1 box)
  This series contains material arranged alphabetically by subject.
  - American National Theatre and Academy, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - Century Club, 1970-1986 (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - C.I.R.C.L.E., [1981] (Box 3, Folder 46)
  - de Liagre, Alfred, 1930, 1934, 1977, 1978, 1980, 1984-1987, undated (Box 3, Folder 47)
  - Financial documents, 1947, 1974, 1982, 1983, 1986, undated (Box 3, Folder 48)
  - Individuals F-T, 1956, 1983, undated (Box 3, Folder 49)
  - Memorabilia, undated (Box 3, Folder 50)
  - Notes, 1982, 1984, undated (Box 3, Folder 51)
  - Plumstead Playhouse, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 52)
  - Speeches, 1950, 1972, 1977, undated (Box 3, Folder 53)
  - Theatrical productions
    - Legal and financial documents, 1949, 1950, undated (Box 3, Folder 54)
    - Printed material
      - B-T, 1941, 1947, 1950, 1953, 1965, 1981, undated (Box 3, Folder 55)
      - J.B.
        - Programs
          - 1958, 1959, 1960 October-Dec, 1961 February-Apr, undated (Box 3, Folder 56-63)
        - Press clippings
          - 1958, 1959, 1960 January-Mar, Jun, October-Dec, 1961, 1970, undated (Box 3, Folder 64-68)
      - Kwamina, 1961 March-August (Box 3, Folder 69)
      - Kwamina, 1961 September-November (Box 3, Folder 70)
      - The Madwoman of Chaillot, 1951 (Box 3, Folder 71)
      - On Your Toes, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 72)
  - Yale University, [1950], 1970, 1985-1987 (Box 3, Folder 73)
- PHOTOGRAPHS, 1927-1977; Series III; .25' (2 boxes)
  - de Liagre, Alfred, 1934, [1943], 1969, 1970, 1977, [1986], undated (Box 4, Folder 74)
  - Theatrical productions
    - B-V, 1932, 1934, 1939, 1945, undated (Box 4, Folder 75)
    - The Madwoman of Chaillot, [1949] (Box 4, Folder 76)
    - Second Threshold, [1951] (Box 4, Folder 77)
    - The Tumbler, [1960] (Box 4, Folder 78)
    - Yes, My Darling Daughter, 1939 (Box 4, Folder 79)
    - Unidentified, undated (Box 4, Folder 80)
  - Oversized photographs
    - Actors
      - P-S (Box 5, Folder 81)
      - Katherine Cornell and Tyrone Power in The Dark is Light Enough (Box 5, Folder 82)
      - Alfred Lunt and Lynn Fontanne (various productions), 1927, 1928, 1939, undated (Box 5, Folder 83)
      - Unidentified, undated (Box 5, Folder 84)
- Additional material, 1933-1978; Accession 2010-M-082
  - Photographs
    - Bubbling Brown Sugar, Theatre de Paris, 1978 September 24 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - By Your Leave, Morosco Theatre, 1934 January 24 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Cat on a Hot Tin Roof, ANTA Theater, 1974 September 24 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Deathtrap, Music Box Theatre, 1978 February 26 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - The Deep Blue Sea, Morosco Theater, 1952 November 5 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - The Druid Circle, Morosco Theatre, 1947 October 22 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Escapade, 48th Street Theatre, 1953 November 12 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Fresh Fields, Empire Theatre, 1936 February 10 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - The Girls in 509, Belasco Theatre, 1958 October 15 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - The Golden Apple, Alvin Theatre, 1954 April 20 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - The Irregular Verb To Love, Ethel Barrymore Theatre, 1963 September 18 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - J.B., ANTA Theatre, 1958 December 11 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Janus, Plymouth Theatre, 1955 November 24 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Kwamina, 54th Street Theatre, 1961 October 23 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Love in E-Flat, Brooks Atkinson Theatre, 1967 February 13 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - The Madwoman of Chaillot, Belasco Theatre, 1948 December 27 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - The Mermaids Singing, Empire Theatre, 1945 November 28 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Mr. and Mrs. North, Belasco Theatre, 1941 January 12 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Nature's Way, Coronet Theatre, 1957 October 16 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - No Code to Guide Her, Playhouse Theatre, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Our Town, ANTA Theater, 1969 November 27 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Petticoat Fever, Ritz Theatre, 1935 March 4 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Photo Finish, Brooks Atkinson Theatre, 1963 February 12 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - The Pure in Heart, Longacre Theatre, 1934 March 20 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      Actual performance photographs taken by Lester-Pickett.
    - Second Threshold, Morosco Theatre, 1951 January 2 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Three-Cornered Moon, Cort Theatre, 1933 March 16 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - The Tumbler, Helen Hayes Theatre, 1960 February 24 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - The Voice of the Turtle, Morosco Theatre, 1943 December 8 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - The Walrus and the Carpenter, Cort Theatre, 1941 November 8 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Yes, My Darling Daughter, The Playhouse, 1937 February 9 (Box 1, Folder 6)